Hello everyone.
So I'm here in Gothenburg with Johan
Carlsson recording the podcast,
but he was also kind enough to
show us the SSRF in GitLab that
he exploited in a very clever way.
It's not the typical full read
SSRF where you just read the
metadata and you have the impact.
It's the one when he actually had
to work hard to get the critical
impact and the good payout.
And he will walk us through the bug today.
so enjoy the video.
can you tell us please, what's the
functionality where the, bug started?
So this bug was in a fairly new
functionality, that it was, they
called it analytic dashboards.
It's like a, a third party integration
thing where you could get data and
send data to an analytic service
that would monitor, yeah, how your
application is used and that's,
something that you configure as a
URL as a third party website, right?
Yeah, exactly.
And for the context of this
bug a bit later, I think that
originally you configure this as
an administrator on the platform.
So you configured a set of, an analytic,
analytic dashboard, a set of features
that GitLab also provides as a Docker
or not the Docker, or even worse,
like a Kubernetes cluster thing.
and, And then you, so yeah, so you
provide it with four different, URLs,
to four different services running
inside of this Kubernetes cluster on
different ports and stuff like that.
and, what I found then was that all
of these were in different ways,
suspect to, SSRF, but only one of
them were like a full read where
you can actually get the error back.
The other ones were blind and
like semi blind and really blind.
Yeah.
How did it happen that one
of them returned the body?
Yeah, that was, when you look at
the source code, it was just like
one of them had, just that it was
treating, it was trying to treat
whatever it got back as a Jason.
And they had, not their like general error
message when things break, they just sent
you back whatever the JSON parsing did.
So you got back like an error,
like we cannot parse this.
And then you got like
this giant payload back.
Yeah.
And so how did you show
the impact of this?
Yeah.
So I think it's the reason why I
chose to highlight this bug is because
I think it, it proves how you can
gain a higher impact by knowing.
And, in this particular case, this
bug went from, I reported this
as a high because I had a full
read and I thought that's usually
a high or it at least could be.
and then it got, I managed to first move
it to critical and then it get bigger.
Pushed down to medium again,
and then I threw some fighting,
got it back to critical again.
Yeah, it was a
long read.
Yeah, it was a long ride.
So the idea here was that I could
get a full read both on, my,
internal or like my self hosted
instance, but also on the, prod.
instance, where I could actually
poke around in whatever they
have in their infrastructure.
I didn't really find
anything super sensitive.
they have had one critical SSRF in
the past, which was this Grafana
SSRF thing, where I think that Justin
managed to actually show some real
impact in the production, at least,
poke at some real, systems there.
And I think they've hardened
it quite a lot since then.
so I focused, a bit more
on my self hosted instance.
Yeah.
To how does, if I can interrupt,
how does GitLab rate the severity
more based on the, your GitLab co
instance or the self hosted one,
which, is the most important one?
No, it's actually the same.
You can get the highest bounty, both
for the, the self hosted and the.
The.
com one, you just have to, prove
that it's not something that you
have to like misconfigure, then it
might be lowered, even for the S.
So in this case, I wanted to show, if you
just install it normally using their, like
the packaged, version they have, and if I
just install it and I could trigger this
and it could get like a critical impact,
then that's enough to get a full critical.
Cool.
So how did you achieve this?
Yeah, I started to look at different
services that are So when you install
GitLab locally or as a Docker instance,
they spin up a bunch of services that they
actually list in their documentation, like
all the ports where things are running.
So you don't really have to
do any scanning or whatever.
You can just try it out and see if any of
them have something interesting to use.
so I looked at that list and I
also tried to read all of the old
SSRF reports I could find from
GitLab, and I didn't find anything
that managed to put it higher than
a high, yeah.
essentially, but I did find, which
I think, you corrected me before
her, but the, someone has collected
like a list of blind necess r Yeah.
the asset note
blind necess R of chain
recall we have, yeah.
so on that list, there's actually like a.
A small SSRF gadget from GitLab where they
mentioned the, Redis exporter, which is a
small tool that is used by, I think it's
used by Prometheus to gain like statistics
to show you about your instance.
And this Redis exporter has a
path that is called slash scrape.
And then you can give it a
URL as a query parameter.
Yeah.
And in the old asset note list, they
just show you that you can point it to
an IP address of the Redis instance.
And then you can get like keys and
values from the Redis instance back.
Oh, so it's Designed to pull
things out of the Redis instance.
Yeah.
Okay.
And it's quite different from the
other, they have a lot of exporters,
But, and usually because Prometheus
is supposed to show like metadata
and statistics and stuff like that.
So usually they don't contain anything
sensitive, the things that you can export.
But this Redis exporter is a bit different
because it gives you keys and values
and that's what you use Redis for.
You store these keys and values in
there and potentially they could
be dangerous than was my thought.
Yeah.
but it, so it happened now that.
Nowadays, apparently they are not
exposing Redis, on an IP anymore.
I guess they used to do it when asset
notes found this gadget, but what I found
out was that this Redis exporter also
could work with Unix sockets, which is.
If you're, I'm not like, low
level hacker, but a Unix socket is
some sort of, network, low level
piece.
It's something I didn't know.
You can talk to when you have the SSR.
That's for sure.
no.
And I guess you cannot really do it
usually from like a web context, but
this exporter it's built in a way that
it can talk to Redis through, yeah.
A socket as well, because
Redis is also talking this
really, low level TCP language.
Yeah.
which also previously you could get RCE
just by talking to a Redis through HDP.
Yeah.
But they have, removed that,
exploitation vector as well.
No, but so I figured out that
I could point to this red
incident and then you could.
Also, when you give it this URL, you
could also give it another parameter
that limits what you search for.
So you can search for a word and put
a star in, and you can like search for
different keys in the Redis instance.
And at that point, I thought it was
Hi again, because you can get data,
but I don't really know what they
store in the, in Redis in GitLab.
So I wanted to find
something juicy in there.
So I started, you can also then
when you host your own GitLab
instance, you can monitor so you can.
log into the instance through SSH and you
can start monitoring the logs from Redis.
And I just, started like tailing and
graphing through the logs while using
GitLab to see if something interesting.
So I created tokens, like connected
some, tokens to my account and
stuff like that to see if something
of it like ended up in, in Redis.
And I got some hits somewhere Ephemeral,
like you could see them for a really
short period and then they disappeared.
So that could be something you
could report, And then I also
found that you could get like SSRF,
no, CSRF tokens for all sessions.
So you could get the IP and the token
that is connected to that session.
So you could scrape all of the CSRF
tokens and then make a POC page where
you match the IP who's coming in.
Is, in
GitLab CSRF token enough to get the CSRF?
yeah,
Because the cookies are, none.
Oh, that's very kind.
yeah.
that vector could be abused as well.
So I wrote that first, but that's
also not really critical because you
have to have a lot of using triggers.
interaction.
Yeah.
And also you would have to have the
JavaScript code that would match the IP
of the CSRF token and hope it's enough.
Yeah, it's a
bit, it's a bit complex, but
then eventually I stumbled on to
something because I was like going
through all of the tokens and
stuff in my head, like sensitive
things that you can do with GitLab.
And then I tried out creating
and connecting a GitLab runner.
And the GitLab runner is when you're
working on GitLab or GitHub or
anything else, you have this concept
of storing your code, but then you
also have the concept of running
pipelines or build jobs or, all of
these other, like CI, CD, DevOps things.
Yeah.
and those in the context of GitLab,
these are running on separate
servers that are called the runners.
And a runner is registered with the token.
And then when the runner is idle, it
will start like pulling the GitLab
instance, like I'm ready for work.
And then if someone has a project that
is connected to this runner and they have
a job, they will say this is my new job.
And the runner will say
okay, I take that job.
It will pull the session and it
can pull the code and it will run
the code and do all the CI things.
So the runner authenticates
using the token?
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, okay.
And it starts like
picking jobs using that.
And then the idea is that you
shouldn't really need to care
which runner you are using.
Like they are the same if you have
allowed them to be used in your project.
Yeah.
So what I found then was quite
interesting was that they actually
used that token as a part of the ID
in the key, value, in Redis.
Yeah.
So that was stored like
indefinitely for what I could see.
So you could actually ask for, you
would ask for the beginning of the
key, which was always the same.
And then you would put a star there
and then you would get the a list of
all the runner tokens on the instance.
And using these runner tokens, you
could then create your own runner,
connect to the GitLab instance and
say okay, I want all of these jobs.
Yeah.
So there was no sort of IP
validation of the runners.
It was just, no, at
least not, like in the,
in a base scenario.
And this is also something they
warn about in the documentation.
They say this token is supposed
to be secret because if.
You find it, you will be able to
impersonate the runner and run jobs.
And what that sort of creates in
the end is actually RCE then in all
of the runner jobs on the GitLab.
Yeah.
Because runner has access
to all the source code.
Yeah.
Does it has push, access as well?
yeah, depending on what it's supposed
to do, but it will definitely be.
what a runner job usually does is
that it's build things, it runs tests
and stuff, it might push artifacts
and it will, it could deploy code in
production or in different places.
And yeah, in a way you have
all the keys to the kingdom.
So that's,
the best thing.
How much time did it take you?
Cause I assume you had the SSRF.
And then you just spend a lot of time
using different features to see if
there's something sensitive in the Redis.
Yeah.
So how much time did it take for
you to finally find this feature
that, gave you the critical?
I think I spent like a week or two.
I also had to, but not like full time.
It's like tinkering on, like thinking
about new ways of exploiting,
because I also was at the same time,
like fighting with the triagers.
So GitLab hadn't even seen the bug.
Yeah, really.
Yeah.
so I just had it like in the back of my
mind, like I want to exploit this more.
So I just thought about different
things and tested out and,
and so from the beginning, I actually
found this through code review,
because they were using a feature.
They were actually using a safe.
A wrapper to send HTTP requests,
which they also always use, but they,
had put in the flag, allow local
requests or something like that.
and that flag is used only when
they know that it's safe to do this.
So I assume that they first built
this for the admin, side of GitLab.
And then they exposed it to, like groups
and projects to configure on their own.
Cause could any user configure this?
Yeah.
At the point when I found it, you
can just be a regular user with
your own project and you can,
so that's why it was critical because
there was no privilege required.
Yeah.
They will put it as
privilege required low.
but it is a self registration
now, so this is the,
yeah, but on the self So they have
in their scope policy, like a special
edge case that they always treat, if
you need an account, it will be low.
And that's because on self hosted
instances, it's not guaranteed.
Oh, cause there's
no always self signup.
No, exactly.
Okay.
Fair enough.
Yeah.
But the rest was like, top.
So that's why.
Yeah, so exactly.
So then you could just go in there
and you could get, I don't think that
they put anything else, any lower.
Yeah, and the scope was changed then.
I guess that's part of, SSRF,
to begin with, I'm not sure.
Scope is really hard to, yeah, but I
guess if you have different companies,
you can leak data from readies.
Yeah.
And
and you're actually in the runner then,
which is a separate application as well.
Yeah.
yeah,
cool.
Nice.
Congratulations for that.
Thank you.
if you enjoyed it, listen to our whole
interview that will be published.
About two weeks after this bug
is published, we'll talk about
way more interesting things.
So for now, thank you
for watching and goodbye.